Guide to the William Motherwell letters and notes, 1833-1834 MS 334
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Motherwell letters and notes
1833-1834
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Motherwell, William
MS 334
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder of 26 items)
Letters and fragments of notes by William Motherwell with no common theme other than the frequent mention of Robert Burns.
Biographical Sketch
William Motherwell, Scottish poet and editor, was born in Glasgow in 1797. He studied classics at Glasgow University from 1818-1819 before becoming Sheriff-clerk at Paisley. He later was deputy Sheriff-clerk of the county of Renfrewshire from 1819-29. Motherwell always wrote in his spare time and in 1828 undertook to edit the 'Paisley Magazine'. From 1828-1830 he also carried out the editorial duties of the 'Paisley Advertiser'. After 1830 the poet moved back to his native Glasgow and worked, again in an editorial capacity, on the 'Glasgow Courier' until his death. In 1835 Motherwell helped produce an edition of Burns' poetry along with a small biographical account of Burns. A self-confessed participant in the Orange movement, Motherwell was called to London in 1835 to testify before a special committee set up to investigate Orangeism. His performance before that tribunal was confused and perhaps showed signs of mental instability. He was returned to Scotland almost immediately. He died of apoplexy soon after. The year was 1835.
Scope and Contents
This Collection contains 26 items representing fragments of William Motherwell's writings from the later years of his life.There appears to be no overall uniting theme to the collection other than the frequent mention of Burns in both the notes and the letters to A. Fullerton (a Glasgow publisher). The items in this collection are probably drawn from the period 1833-1834.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This material was purchased from Black's; see Black's Catalogue no. 36 (1954) item no. 18. Purchased in by the Woodson Research Center from the Friends' fund (Whittington gift).
Index Terms
Document Types
notes
Subjects (Persons)
Motherwell, William; Burns, Robert
- Series I: Notes and letters, 1833-34 (Folder 1)
  - Item 1 Letter from William Motherwell to unknown, November 4, 1833, 1920-1976
  - Item 2 Letter from William Motherwell to unknown, December 28, 1833
  - Item 3 Letter from William Motherwell to unknown, March 18, 1834
  - Item 4 Notes by William Motherwell, n.d. page 3
  - Item 5 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "Twa Days," n.d., page 9
  - Item 6 Notes by William Motherwell, n.d., page 17
  - Item 7 Essay by William Motherwell, "Death of Nornbork," n.d., page 38
  - Item 8 Essay by William Motherwell, "Brigs of Ayr," n.d., page 46
  - Item 9 Notes by William Motherwell, "The Order When," n.d., page 50
  - Item 10 Notes by William Motherwell, Re: "Notes to the Devil," n.d., page 52
  - Item 11 Notes (or poem) by William Motherwell, n.d., page 56
  - Item 12 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "Address to the Devil," n.d., page 57
  - Item 13 Notes by William Motherwell, n.d., page 62
  - Item 14 Notes by William Motherwell, n.d., pages 63-68
  - Item 15 Notes by William Motherwell, n.d., page 70
  - Item 16 Notes by William Motherwell, n.d., page 82
  - Item 17 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "Halloween,", n.d., page 91
  - Item 18 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "Cotters Saturday Night,", n.d., page 134
  - Item 19 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "Mountain Daisy,", n.d., page 144
  - Item 20 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "Epistle to Mankind," n.d., page 183
  - Item 21 Letter by William Motherwell to J.A. Fullerton, n.d.
  - Item 22 Letter by William Motherwell to J.A. Fullerton, n.d.
  - Item 23 Letter by William Motherwell to J.A. Fullerton, n.d., January 1931-January 1934
  - Item 24 Letter by William Motherwell to unknown, n.d.
  - Item 25 Notes by William Motherwell Re: "The Ethick Shepherd," n.d.
  - Item 26 Notes by William Motherwell Re: Robert Burns, n.d.